Guide to the Merton Bernfield Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Merton Bernfield papers
1974-1987
SC0767
Bernfield, Merton
17 Linear feet (13 boxes)
These papers pertain only to Bernfield's teaching in the Program in Human Biology at Stanford University and include syllabi, lectures, exams, course readers, memoranda, slides used in the classes, and other papers.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Merton Bernfield was a pediatrician and cell biologist whose research led to a greater understanding of the architecture of human tissue. He earned his medical degree at the University of Illinois and later was a research associate with Marshall Nirenberg, the Nobel Prize-winning geneticist, at the National Heart Institute before coming to Stanford in 1967. He taught at Stanford for 22 years as professor in the medical school and in the university's School of Humanities and Sciences, serving as chair of the Program in Human Biology, associate director of the birth defects clinic at Stanford Hospital and co-director of its premature infant follow-up clinic. He joined the Harvard Medical School faculty in 1989 as the Clement Smith Professor of Pediatrics and Cell Biology and Director of the Joint Program in Neonatology at the Children’s Hospital, Boston.
Description of the Collection
These papers pertain only to Bernfield's teaching in the Program in Human Biology at Stanford University and include syllabi, lectures, exams, course readers, memoranda, slides used in the classes, and other papers.
Access Terms
Bernfield, Merton; Stanford University. Program in Human Biology.; Biology--Study and teaching (Higher); Human physiology.
Collection Contents
- Human Biology 3A Lecture Notes, 1981-1982 winter (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Human Biology 3A Review and Exams, 1981-1982 winter (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Human Biology Notes, 1978 winter (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Human Biology Lecture Notes, 1979 fall (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Human Biology Lecture Notes, The Cell Periphery, 1979 fall (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Human Biology Lecture Notes, Endomembrane System, 1979 fall (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Human Biology Lecture Notes, Cell Movement + Cell Shape + Module: Lactation, 1979 fall (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Human Biology Lecture Notes, The Genetic Functions of DNA + Regulations of Protein Synthesis, 1979 fall (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Human Biology Lecture Notes, Berg Module: Recombinant DNA + General Outline, 1979 fall (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Human Biology 123, 1985 spring (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Human Biology 19: Scientific Thinking, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
- Human Biology 123, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Human Biology 2A/2B Lecture Notes, 2A Handouts, Review Sheets, Exams, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Human Biology 2A/2B Lecture Notes, 2B Handouts, Review Sheets, Exams, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Human Biology 2A/2B Lecture Notes, 2B ASSU Notes, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Human Biology 123 Master Notes, 1987 spring (Box 2, Folder 4-7)
- Human Biology 3A, 1987 winter (Box 2, Folder 8-10)
- Human Biology 2 Human Evolution: Genetics + Culture (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Human Biology 3A Winter Quarter, Administration + Review Sheets, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Human Biology 3A Winter Quarter, Handouts, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Human Biology 3A Winter Core Notes (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Human Biology Winter 3A Core, Binder--Notes, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Test Bank I, Binder--Sample Exam Questions (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Test Bank II, Binder--Sample Exam Questions (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Human Biology 3A, Notes, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
- Human Biology, Notes, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Human Biology, Notes, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Human Biology Lecture Notes, 1977 spring-fall (Box 4, Folder 2)
- L.O.H.M.B.L./ W.H.M.B.L. Lab Course, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Human Biology Executive Committee, 1983-1987 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
- Human Biology Upper Division Committee 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
- Human Biology Pre-74 Outlines (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Human Biology Memos (Box 5, Folder 1)
- AB Admin matters and 40/41 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Human Biology General Info, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Human Biology Core Planning, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Core (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Rob Dorit (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Commonwealth Report (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Core Syllabi, 1975-1977 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- General, Chairman's File (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Notes to Deans: Royden, Wessells, Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Policy Course Info (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Human Biology (old) (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Law Birth? Human Biology 123 Transparencies, 1985 May (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Human Biology 123 “Biological and Policy Aspects of Fetal Development” Course and topic Outlines and Ref. Lists (Org) (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Human Biology 123 Handouts File Copies (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Human Biology 85 Lectures (Box 5, Folder 16)
- IVF/ET/Surrogacy? (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Human Biology 123: Biological and Policy Aspects of Fetal Development, Course Reader, copy 1, 1985 spring (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Human Biology 123: Biological and Policy Aspects of Fetal Development, Course Reader, copy 2, 1985 spring (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Human Biology 3A Course Reader, 1984 winter (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Human Biology 40: Health and Public Policy: Regulation, Course Reader, 1978 winter (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Human Biology 40: Health and Public Policy: Birth Control Course Reader (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Human Biology 3A Course Reader, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Human Biology 3A Reading Packet, 1987 winter (Box 6, Folder 6)
- IUGR (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Human Biology 123, Mnookin, 1987 Mar (Box 6, Folder 8)
- IUF (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Human Biology 123 Low Birth Weight Lecture Transparencies (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Sierra LBW + IVF, 1985 Jul (Box 7, Folder 3)
- PREM Module (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Poverty and PLBW (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Human Biology 123 Syllabus (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Human Biology 123 Intro (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Student Reports (Box 7, Folder 8)
- JSDB Talk (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Abortion Lecture Notes (Box 7, Folder 10)
- LAMB Human Biology 123 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Human Biology 123 Capp’s Outlines Fuch’s questions/report (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Human Biology Papers, 1987 Jun (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Review on the Program in Human Biology, Bound Report, 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Letters--outgoing correspondence (Box 7, Folder 15-16)
- Ethnic differences (Box 7, Folder 17)
- Human Biology, 1974-1976 (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Human Biology--Scientific American, etc.? (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Human Biology, 1976-1977 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Pediatrics 205 Abnormal Human Development Spring, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Human Biology Transparencies, 1976 Oct 4 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Advisory Committee PRC (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Fetus at Environmental Risk (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Human Biology 2A Introduction to the Cell, 1978 Oct 9 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Human Biology 2A Cell Function I: Membranes and Transport, 1978 Oct 11 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Human Biology 2A Cell Function II: Organelles and Macromolecules, 1978 Oct 16 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Human Biology 2A Cell Function III: More Organelles and Macromolecules, 1978 Oct 16 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Human Biology 2A, 1978 Oct 18 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Human Biology 2A, 1978 Oct 20 (Box 8, Folder 12)
- [Human Biology 2A?], 1978 Oct 23 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- #1: 1978 Feb 1 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- #2: 1978 Feb 3 (Box 8, Folder 15)
- #3: 1978 Feb 6 (Box 8, Folder 16)
- #4: 1978 Feb 8 (Box 8, Folder 17)
- #5 1978 Feb 10 (Box 8, Folder 18)
- Feb. 13, 15, and 17th [1978?] (Box 8, Folder 19)
- Human Biology 3A Human Organism, 1978-1979 winter (Box 8, Folder 20)
- Pictures, 1978 winter (Box 8, Folder 21)
- Human Biology 3A Lecture #1, 1979 Jan 5-10 (Box 8, Folder 22)
- Human Biology 3A, 1979 Jan 12-15 (Box 8, Folder 23)
- Human Biology 3A, 1979 Jan 17-22 (Box 8, Folder 24)
- [Human Biology 3A?], 1979 Jan 24-26 (Box 8, Folder 25)
- Human Biology lectures, Johnson slides (Box 8, Folder 26)
- Human Biology 19 (Box 8, Folder 27)
- Human Biology 2A, Cells and Their Organization, 1979 Oct 22 (Box 8, Folder 28)
- Human Biology 2A, The Cell Periphery, 1979 Oct 24 (Box 8, Folder 29)
- Human Biology 2A, Endomembrane Systems, 1979 Oct 26 (Box 8, Folder 30)
- Human Biology 2A, Cell Movement and Cell Shape, 1979 Oct 29 (Box 8, Folder 31)
- Human Biology 2A, The Genetic Functions of DNA, 1979 Nov 2 (Box 8, Folder 32)
- Human Biology 2A, Nucleus and Cell Reproduction, 1979 Nov 14 (Box 8, Folder 33)
- Human Biology 3A, Introduction to Human Development, 1980 Jan 9-14 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Human Biology 3A, Early Human Development, 1980 Jan 16-18 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Human Biology 3A, The Human Fetus, Birth and Adaptation to Extrauterine Life, 1980 Jan 21-25 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Human Biology 3A Module: Premature Birth, 1980 Jan 28 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Xeroxes from Karp’s Cell Biology (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Unlabeled folder of notes (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Human Biology 3A Lecture Notes, File Copy, (“likely duplicate”), 1986 winter (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Human Biology 123: Biological and Policy Aspects of Fetal Development (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Selected Readings on Policy Issues in Abortion and Fetal Research JPaper clipped articles and listing, 1975 Jan 15 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Human Biology 4: Abortion and Fetal Research, Course Reader and articles, copy 1, 1976 spring (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Human Biology 4: Abortion and Fetal Research, Course Reader and articles, copy 2, 1976 spring (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Human Biology Lecture Notes, 1978 fall (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Human Biology 3A Core, Binder--Slides (Box 10)
- C. Teaching 16-29, Binder--Slides Only, 1981-1982 winter (Box 10)
- D. Mammary Proteoglycans 30.33.34.35, Binder--Slides Only (Box 10)
- Epithelial Morphogenesis Sections 5-15, Binder--Slides Only (Box 11)
- F. Immunology – Histology PG 39, 40, Binder--Slides Only (Box 11)
- 11F of Salv and Skin, Binder--Slides Only (Box 11)
- E. Cell Surface Proteoglycan 32.36-38, Binder--Slides Only (Box 11)
- G. Clinical Research I 41-42/H. Clinical Research II 43-46, Binder--Slides Only (Box 12)
- Human Biology 3A, Binder--Slides, 1987 (Box 12)
- Smooth Muscle Growth, Binder--Slides Only (Box 12)
- Human Biology, Binder--Slides, 1989-1990 (Box 12)
- Epithelial Morphogenesis Sections 1-4, Binder--Slides Only (Box 13)